At some point in history, a human asked
the first question, striking the flint
of comprehension against the pyrite of
uncertainty.
In that moment, the first true spark of
humanity's self-awareness was produced.
A spark destined to light the world on
fire.
Self-awareness is generally considered a
good thing.
As a result of our unique human form of
self-awareness, we can conceptually
comprehend ourselves [music] in the
world, abstractly recall and foresee
events, form rationales about the things
that happen, and strive [music] to
change them.
These abilities are undeniably profound.
They have played a fundamental role in
our rising to the top of the animal
kingdom, overcoming the inhibitions of
our biology, and conquering much of the
world. But self-awareness can also be a
terrible thing.
Because of our particular form of it, we
can also recognize our own limits.
We can perceive, with grave intensity,
our ignorance, meekness, futility, and
suffering. As individuals capable of
comprehending, imagining, and
rationalizing, we are naturally
compelled toward understanding,
controlling, and mattering.
The problems caused by our
self-awareness begin here, with the
contrast between what we are compelled
toward and what we are capable of.
Although we are granted the ability to
comprehend some of ourselves in reality,
and although we can conquer so much of
the world, ultimately, we do not seem to
possess the ability to truly control,
understand, [music]
or conquer ourselves.
As a species, we don't really know what
we want. Human progress, both
individually and collectively, is often
passionate, but also largely blind and
aimless, all roads apparently leading
toward futility and oblivion.
Even if we knew what we wanted, all
evidence seems to suggest that we would
only struggle indefinitely to attain it.
We can never quite dig deeply enough
into ourselves in the world to know
what's at [music] play, to know what
mechanisms of nature are in operation,
why they work the way they do, and how
or whether we can fundamentally alter
how they work.
We will never obtain what we are truly
after. We can never conquer reality and
know truth.
Every new discovery will inevitably fall
victim to the next. Every attempt at
meaning will inevitably reveal itself to
be an illusion.
The more tightly we try to hold on to
the world,
>> [music]
>> the more our hands will callous.
Ultimately, we almost watch ourselves as
we struggle against these
inevitabilities. We must witness our
failures, our absurdities, and our
deaths as we strive endlessly with a
reasonably clear view, but no clear
direction.
It is as if we were given access to the
show of existence [music]
with a desire for a directorial role,
but with intense lucidity. We are forced
to sit in the audience as things go
wrong over [music] and over.
The cultural anthropologist Ernest
Becker brilliantly summarizes our
existential plight in The Denial of
Death.
Man has a symbolic identity that brings
him sharply out of nature. He is a
symbolic self, a creature with a name, a
life history.
He is a creator with a mind that soars
out to speculate about atoms and
infinity. Yet, at the same time, man is
a worm and food for [music] worms. This
is the paradox. He is out of nature and
hopelessly in it.
>> [music]
>> He is dual, up in the stars and yet
housed in a heart-pumping,
breath-gasping body that once belonged
to a fish and still carries the gill
marks to prove it.
It is a terrifying dilemma to be in and
to have to live with.
Of course, the problems of
self-awareness are by no means new.
They began at the onset of
consciousness, and then, arguably, they
became more and more inflamed throughout
human history through the cognitive
revolution, agricultural revolution,
scientific revolution, industrial
revolutions, and technological
revolutions.
But now, particularly because of the
rapid progress of science and
technology, we are suddenly more aware
of ourselves and the world than any
humans have ever been before.
>> [music]
>> We are more aware of the horrors and
paradoxes of our existence.
Moreover, because of the modernization
and Westernization of so much of the
world, we are also more compelled to
understand, [music] control, and
eradicate these horrors and paradoxes.
Western society has largely chosen
reason, order, control, and certainty
[music] as its weapons in the war
against the universe.
But every battle is fought in a war that
cannot be won.
The universe feels no pain. We feel the
pain for it. The war is thus with
ourselves.
We have been and will always be the
victims of our own tactics.
Over time, though we have increasingly
prospered in areas like safety,
security, health, and longevity, we
have, arguably, declined in areas like
our sense of meaning, purpose,
connection, and clarity. Previous myths
and imagined orders that depended on
humanity's ignorance have fallen
increasingly to the wayside, killed off
by new knowledge and theories. Folklore,
mythologies, religions, traditions,
these things have been sacrificed to our
increasing awareness.
In the words of author H.P. Lovecraft,
"The most merciful thing in the world, I
think, is the inability of the human
mind to correlate all its contents. We
live on a placid island of ignorance in
the midst of black seas of infinity. And
it was not meant that we should voyage
far. The sciences, each straining in its
own direction, have hitherto harmed us
little. But someday the piecing together
of dissociated knowledge will open up
such terrifying vistas of reality and of
our frightful position therein that we
shall either go mad from the revelation
or flee from the deadly light into the
peace and safety of a new dark age."
The someday that Lovecraft wrote about
nearly 100 years ago is, arguably,
today.
The human project appears to be one
lifelong response to having woken up to
these terrifying vistas, the conditions
of reality and consciousness, and then
trying to outrun them by running further
into them.
And now, we have fully opened them up,
and they cannot be escaped.
Thus, confronting the pains and problems
of self-awareness has only become
increasingly crucial.
It is not hopeless.
Although our self-awareness causes much
of our suffering, it is also the
lifeline with which we can manage and
endure it. Self-awareness is the means
by which we can transmute and transcend
our suffering.
More crucially and powerfully than
anything else, because of our awareness,
we are uniquely able to discover and
interpret immense beauty and wonder,
despite what we cannot do or know, and
despite how terrifying everything might
be.
Not only are we able to exist and
survive, but we can exist and survive in
the name of ideas and wonders that we
forge for ourselves.
With proper attention and effort, we can
weave meaning out of our bodies, our
minds, our nature, our history, and our
future, like a tapestry of possibility
and achievement. We can know ourselves
and know that we know [music] ourselves.
We can know the borders of knowledge and
struggle against them, pushing like a
child might against a heavy piece of
furniture that they have no business
moving. But, if it even moves an inch,
joy floods the veins.
We can transfigure suffering into
meaning through art, curiosity, [music]
and aesthetic experiences.
We can know why it means so much to draw
close to another being. We can know what
it means to love. And we can choose to
love it all.
This is the terrible paradox of
self-awareness.
Our awareness causes our suffering,
>> [music]
>> but our suffering can be made worthwhile
through our awareness.
The task is not to resolve this paradox,
however,
but to utilize
and embrace it.
That was the introduction to my new
book, The Terrible Paradox of
Self-Awareness. It's out now, and you
can get your copy through the link in
the description.
If you enjoy my work and enjoy Pursuit
of Wonder, I think you'll really
resonate with this book. It's a series
of reflections on both the burdens and
gifts of self-awareness, [music]
of consciousness, exploring topics like
the self, meaning, truth, desire,
suffering, futility, time, death, and
hope. It's for those of us who know that
existence is irredeemably absurd, but
nonetheless seek to commune with the
absurdity, to live well within the
condition of a mind that formed without
us in mind. It's an entirely new
non-fiction work of mine, perhaps
simultaneously my darkest and most
hopeful work yet. If you have or do
choose to get a copy, thank you so much.
Your support on this project truly means
a lot.
>> [music]
>> And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general, and see
you next video.